Oh Vasudeva suitum daivam come such are
no Dumber Dunham
dave aqui para maana and krishna monday
jagadguru so in the bhagavad-gita is
studying the second chapter we are at a
point of inflection that means the point
of change now the subject matter is
going to be changed now until this point
Sri Krishna had taught Gyana yoga the
central teaching of the bhagavad-gita
the doctrine of the Atman that we are
not the body not the mind we are
immortal spirit pure consciousness so
that's what he had taught and also and
now he's going to talk about karma yoga
how to transform our actions into
spiritual practice in between there was
this short interesting section from
verse number 31 to 38 yes where Shri
Krishna used a battery of ethical
arguments practical arguments to
convince Arjuna to do his duty and so
that section has come to an end with the
38 verse which we read last time did we
not read it last time 38 okay okay so
make with 1200 Jo Jo that o you die or
you just for neighbor Papa mo ops you
see regarding pleasure and pain suka
dukkha pleasure and pain alike gain and
loss lavalava
alike victory and defeat Jaya Jaya alike
prepare yourself for doing your duty in
this way you will not incur sin just a
note that these terms are causally
connected if you look if you read
closely you'll see pleasure and pain in
the battle that is going to fight
it comes out of whether he has gained or
lost if he gains Debbie we if we get
gained and we if we are the winners we
gain then we feel happy if we lose then
we feel under dejected a pain and what
is gained in this context it is victory
in battle what is loss in this context
it is defeat in battle so look at the
sequence suka pleasure
is caused by lava that is gained and
lava means Jaya that means victory
dukkha sorrow is caused by a lava that
is loss loss is a Jaya that is not
victory or defeat in battle so it's
actually causally connected but what he
is saying is be Celine in with regard to
these how can you be serene in regard to
this only in one way if you are doing it
as the right thing to do see if you're
doing it for victory which Arjuna was
which is a common sense that were you're
fighting you're do you're do taking up
any action what what do you want to get
out of it if you want worldly success a
worldly success so for Arjuna that meant
big tree that meant a revenge on the
evildoers and so and so forth taking
back what is rightfully belongs to him
and to his brothers but shri krishna
urges him to give up all of that see in
between what has happened is Arjuna came
to the battlefield with all these arby's
for that purpose to get what is
rightfully his and to defeat the evil
doers and so on and so forth now when he
sees the terrible cost of that truly
like any good person he feels it's not
worth it it's not worth it I will gain
something but and what cost my relatives
this is this is a terrible thing to do
and he's right he's right that's a
terrible thing to do faith and if the
thing is his personal gain but what sri
krishna points out is that it's not
really a question of your personal gain
you are in this great dilemma because
you are
it for yourself in a legitimate way in a
righteous winner but not nothing bad
about it but still yourself was central
to it all you're doing it for yourself
but now think about it this way
I am NOT doing it for myself I am doing
it for the welfare of of the kingdom I
am doing it because it is which is what
I am supposed to do my duty in this
situation in that case it makes a huge
difference does it yes it does if you
are doing the right thing you very
convinced that you're doing the right
thing then whether you succeed or not is
not so German is not so important if you
succeed you'll be happy I did the right
thing and I succeeded in doing the right
thing I'm happy I did the right thing
but I failed didn't work out all right
unhappy but still but still it's not as
terrible as I fought a war entirely for
my selfish purposes and and created such
havoc and I failed it's all round
failure then but here he has done the
model thing the ethical thing the good
thing and maybe who knows might have
failed even then it's all right so he
says no Papa my ops you see you will not
incur sin do it with selfish motives
then whatever you do is sinful you're
doing it for yourself so if you win it's
still simple if you if you lose it's
still sinful so the importance of the
mental attitude in action has been
pointed out here but we had done this
now comes the switch in subject
thirty-ninth worse please repeat after
me a shot a vita Sankey a shot a Vita
Sankey boo do Gateway mom Shri no boo do
gateway mom Sri no Buddha yocto Yaya
Budhia Yocto Yaya but karma Bandhan
prophecy karma Bandhan prahasta see the
teaching about the self has been given
teaching about the Atman has been given
to you now
listen to the teaching about action
karma yoga being equipped with which
being endowed with which you will
transcend the bondage created by action
I'll repeat again you have heard that
the teaching about Atman Who am I what
is the reality about our sim myself you
heard that
now listen to the teaching about action
karma yoga what will that do by
practicing that you will transcend the
bondage created by action so it has to
be unpacked and what he will do from now
on is going to unpack it one question
here the teaching about the self Atman
one might ask
I am Bronwyn Zidane and Rupa her
shivoham that was the teaching I am
Brahman I am pure consciousness the
world is an appearance the central
teaching of advaita vedanta taught to
amma see that thou art that has been
given so what else is needed what is
this now why does this topic come up at
all what's the point the point is this
first of all even after giving that that
teaching it often does not work there
might be a rare person who becomes
illumined being told that you are the
Atman you are the witness consciousness
alright done thank you very much
Geeta over half the second chapter and
the whole Gita is finished but Arjuna
like the rest of us has many questions
and many other problems it doesn't
straightaway work philosophy itself
being realized in in life becoming
enlightened directly by the teaching it
might work but for a very few for most
of us we have many other problems so
those things have to be Dell
with then there are other other issues
involved what about I realize I'm the
admin but what about this life I have
got things to do in this life there are
people in my life there this action
there's my life to lead how do I connect
it to my spirituality are there two
things one is spiritual life another
one's secular life if there are two
things you know and that's what happens
to most of us spiritual life Vedanta
Society
Friday evening seven-thirty rest of it
secular life the spiritual life is going
to lose and lose badly why because the
demands of secular life are so tough you
have a family to look after you have a
job to hold you have health problems
financial problems community social
political problems so many pressures on
life that spirituality is nice a talk
now a little bit of mindfulness sometime
a little this and that and good but the
moment some pressure comes we
immediately start dealing with that and
spirituality takes the backseat that
which was meant to solve all the
problems in our life it doesn't help us
in it crisis not only that it sometimes
becomes an additional problem to-do list
so many things to do and also a Gita
class on top of that usually the Gita
class is the first to be sacrificed and
not you because you have taken the
trouble to turn up on a cold day but
it's natural it's natural
I remember the difference between karma
and meditation as a senior monk telling
a novice in our ashram there that as
novices we all had duties so that
novices duty was to to sell books in the
bookshop so he has to maintain the
bookshop the senior monk was telling the
novice I hope you get up early and
meditate see my boy there's nobody who's
going to tell you to do that the
bookshop will make you work
because people will line up and if you
don't open the bookshop they're going to
complain to the senior monk about you
look at the broad burma cherry the
novice is so lazy hasn't opened the
bookshop on time it's not clean it's not
kept nicely this book is not available
and so and so forth so the world will
extract work from you as far as your
external activities are concerned let it
be karmayoga let it be just your
ordinary duties in life the world will
extract it from you will make you
perform but you and God is sitting
quietly in the in the early morning
darkness and meditating on God
God is an easy boss apparently he's not
going to hold you accountable you don't
turn up for meditation all right it's
your loss God has nothing to say it's
going to sit quietly so you're going to
meditate or not meditate there it
depends on you that often happens that
becomes the problem if you split up
spiritual life and secular life so
spiritualizing the whole of life is
important spiritualizing the whole of
life is important because I often hear
this question I talk a lot about on
Twitter Vedanta and people like it but
what common question the most common
question is Swami have heard the talks I
read the books now what now what if a
greater Vedanta works as it is supposed
to work it won't even ask the question
now what but because we asked the
question shri krishna has a new section
beginning now on karma yoga now this
this is what we're going to do there's a
word here - - imam shri knew in sanskrit
- the word is para karana with Jada
thumb which means to differentiate
between two sections of the same chapter
so one section is over now we are
beginning another section IANA yoga is
over Karma Yoga is starting now to Imam
Shin do gong to amounting to a few
before we start a few words about the
terms
used here yes you might ask your using
words like Advaita and Vedanta and Ghani
yoga where is Krishna used such words
so the Krishna uses the words Sankyo now
this is a very old use of the word
Sankhya Sankyo means knowledge here
knowledge about the Atman specifically
knowledge about the Atman the other term
other meaning of the word Sankhya we
know it's a system of philosophy one of
the six systems of Orthodox Hindu
philosophy jnana rachet sheikah Sankhya
yoga yes you heard correctly yoga yoga
is among many meanings of yoga 101 is
the philosophy of yoga yoga purva
mimamsa tara mimamsa six systems that
otero mimamsa the later mimamsa is is
the technical name for vedanta what we
call the atlanta so Sankhya is one of
the systems of philosophy but here it's
that's not what is meant when krishna
says i have taught you Sankhya I've
taught you knowledge about the Atman the
philosophy of Sankhya is also about the
Atman about this self but here
specifically he means I've given you
knowledge about the real nature of the
self till now now yoga but the yoga to
Imam Sri no now listen to the teaching
about yoga what yoga is referring to
here now there were karma yoga so yoga
here refers to karma yoga so the if you
I said Gyana yoga and karma yoga two
sections in Krishna's words Sankhya and
car and Yoga Yoga means karma yoga and
Sankhya means Gianni yoga in our
terminology there is a very ancient
saying they don't know who said it but
it'd be beautiful and very important
saying for our spiritual life sank as
among Yanam nasty yoga yoga cimbalom
nasty there is no knowledge like the
knowledge of the self Sankhya and there
is no power like the power of spiritual
practice yoga in life what do you need
you need knowledge and power you need to
know and the power to do that knowledge
our real nature comes from adwaita
Vedanta Organa yoga and what you have to
do bhakti Yoga karma yoga and Dianna
Raja over those are the three all right
being equipped with this knowledge what
so Arjuna might ask so what what will
happen to me if I get that this
knowledge you will overcome the bondage
created by action karma otherwise
creates bondage keeps us in samsara how
can we use that very Karma to escape
from samsara to get freedom from samsara
so I mean vaikunta say that you cannot
run away from samsara you must learn to
work the machine this is the word in
other words he uses one must learn to
work the machine so that the Machine
sets you free if you try to run they
will be crushed by that machine learn to
work the machine operate the machine so
that it sets you free how do we operate
the machinery of life so that we are
liberated from samsara we get salvation
enlightenment moksha Nirvana that will
be the teaching now another point see
these are the points which commentators
bring out it may not occur to us but
they think very deeply and they have
this if this was the purpose to teach
gana yoga and then karma yoga so after
completing the Gyana yoga teaching which
was in verse 30 up to 30 should have
straight started with this what was that
between 31 and 38 what was that that's
because according to one commentator
when we are going to do karma yoga that
is spiritualizing my Karma
first of all one must know cut off via
Karma that is what am I going to do and
when spiritualize it correct but what is
it that I'm supposed to do what is it
that I'm not supposed to do so from 31
to 38 krishna has clearly pointed out
Arjuna knows this but it needed needed
to be said what is the duty actually
what what should Arjuna do what should
he not do it's a beautiful
of teaching these teachers Krishna
Buddha Christ mama
Shankara all of them and of course
Ramakrishna there were master teachers
if you just look at the pedagogy
involved the way they teach the
communication if you notice in verses 31
to 38 he stated what should be done
first second he stated what should not
be done and finally concluded again with
what should be done in between he
discussed the advantages of doing what
should be done and the disadvantages of
not doing his duty those were discussed
and he draws it to a conclusion in the
end by saying once again stating what he
should do I was in a discussion group
just yesterday by discussing how to
communicate with children modern
psychology so first you have to
acknowledge the situation this is the
problem and this is what you are saying
so an observation acknowledgement then
you have to express a feeling Krishna
does that again and again you'll notice
how he he proclaims that I love you I am
your well-wisher again and again here he
expresses it's not a neutral teaching
from a distance because I am your
well-wisher nobody loves you more than
me
therefore I am saying it and then
express our request this is what you
should do and keep the person's freedom
into intact having said all this you're
still free I'm not putting any pressure
on you at the end of eight 18 chapters
what does Krishna say the last thing he
says is your choice choice he thought ah
guru after having listened to all this
now do as you will I'm done but you are
free to do whatever you want sri krishna
ramakrishna also says that jaya thicker
i'll do it again
actually when a jedi car died the
knowledge of advaita to the hem of your
cloth and then do as you will that means
for base yourself at philosophy and and
on the philosophy
you have non-dualism let that that light
up your mind and then do what you want
what you will but you will winds do
whether you want to be a yogi or a
devotee or a gurney or engaged in
dynamic action for the welfare of the
world whatever you want to do do so
ramakrishna says that the idea tie kora
literally means do whatever you want but
it's it can often be used in Bengali as
a kind of kind of a lot of a scolding
mom's often you use it the exasperated
moms say to children or do whatever you
want to do I give up
so JIT icaro I remember the fight is a
funny incident where there was this
senior Swami in an ashram scolding a
young monk who is a very innocent but
but apt to exasperate the senior monk
sometimes the muck the finally the
senior monk said whatever are you doing
what is this you're doing and the young
monk said didn't swami don't you know
what see Ramakrishna said try the
knowledge of advaitha to the hem of your
cloth and do whatever you like he said
oh so you have tied the knowledge of
advaitha to your clock and the young
monk replied I am trying to do a part of
it at least half of it do whatever you
like so I'm doing that I am practicing
that part I am practicing that part
so first Shri Krishna determines what
has to be done in the verses 31 to 38
now how do you do it spiritually this is
your duty now how do you do it
spiritually that's going to start now
okay there's one more thing I need to
say before I go on notice how karma yoga
is being positioned here Karma Yoga is
being positioned as a means as a
practice to enable you to realize gana
yoga I am the Atman in order to realize
that in my life I need to do these
practices
to prepare myself so the the inner text
the subtext is what we are going to
teach you will not give you
enlightenment or freedom directly but it
will prepare you for the higher
knowledge of the Earthmen repeat that
Karma Yoga is a practice to gain yoga as
a supplement to as a step to gianna yoga
the commentator here sridhar swami this
is one one commentator but this is
typical he says
oopah system Gyana yoga no person Haran
taught siddhanam Karma Yoga impressed ot
having concluded the teaching about jana
the means - that is now being introduced
Karma Yoga is a means to that is being
introduced but this is a maneuver done
by the commentators Krishna never
clearly says that it is a means to Karma
Yoga is a means to gain Yoga later on
you see Swami Vivekananda says each of
them independently can take you there
but the traditional commentators
Shankara for example and Twitter days
they put Gannett knowledge at the top
and others leading up to that so I have
said this earlier but this is the right
time to say it and I'll have an occasion
to repeat it again what is the framework
keep this in mind the framework of
spiritual practice the let us call it
the let's call it the matrix of
spiritual practice what are we to do if
that is the question in spiritual life
to become enlightened to attain moksha
liberation salvation what are we to do
according to Vedanta here is the answer
make a matrix in your mind three by
three in your mind three columns the
first column is problem the second
column is solution the third column is
method problem solution method three
columns
Vedanta tells us you are Brahman your
pure being immortal beyond any any
suffering your pure awareness beyond the
problems of the body be all forever
perfect before ever beyond the problems
of the mind and stops and we are left
sort of scratching our heads that
doesn't quite help me why doesn't seem
to be a living reality to me it doesn't
seem I've heard it I'm not sure I
understand what it means and it
certainly doesn't seem to be a lived
reality to me it's not realized yet it's
not it I'm not awake to that reality
what you're talking about so problem you
said it but I don't realize it I don't
know it not knowing not realizing so the
problem the first problem is Agana
ignorance first problem is our ganna
ignorant what I'm telling now is
absolutely key to understanding
bhagavad-gita from the Vedanta
perspective Advaita Vedanta perspective
so you have to keep it in mind it many
questions you know from now on can be
answered I might just say refer to the
matrix tell me the answer you can easily
get the answer yourself
so what is the matrix first problem is
ignorance or guiana Sanskrit what is the
solution solution knowledge solution for
any problem any ignorant is knowledge
gianna in sanskrit here I'll point out
something which seems obvious but still
good to keep in mind knowledge removes
ignorant correct provided provided there
are two conditions the object and locus
of knowledge and ignorance are the same
object and locus of the knowledge and
ignorance are the same what do you mean
that sounds really difficult no it is
and it's very very it's really simple
really simple it just philosophers love
make simple things difficult what does
it mean suppose I am ignorant the
question will be ignorant of what I'm
ignorant of physics ah so I have
ignorant of physics what is the object
of magnetons what is it that I do not
know physics where is this ignorance in
me in me the student the student is
ignorant of physics
now knowledge will be required to remove
this ignorance remember knowledge must
have the same exam objected same locus
locus means place residence which means
what kind of knowledge is required and
where is that knowledge required
knowledge of mathematics or knowledge of
Sanskrit will not remove my ignorance of
physics knowledge of physics will remove
my ignorance of physics because the
object of knowledge and object of
ignorance must be the same one my
professors knowledge of physics will not
remove mine are ignorant of physics that
knowledge has to come in me it has to
arise in me I must get the feeling that
I must know it in that case the
knowledge is here ignorance was here
that knowledge when it comes here it
will remove the ignorance here so
ignorant about Atman about the self who
I really am that can be removed only by
knowledge of Sanskrit gita knowledge of
Atman yes knowledge of Atman and my
gurus knowledge is not enough Sri
Ramakrishna and Vivekananda knowledge is
not enough to remove my my ignorance it
must come here they can help me but it
must ultimately come here
I must realize it so knowledge removes
ignorant gianna removes a gana problem
ignorant solution knowledge method how
do I get that knowledge shravana monana
needed class and this is gana yoga
shravana monona needed T asana literally
hearing reasoning meditating hearing
reasoning
meditating hearing here means
systematically studying Vedanta which
means coming to class listening
carefully thinking about it asking
questions congratulations you are
already practicing Jana Yoga yes the
moment you have started shravana
listening to vedanta and thinking
applying the mind to it
we're already practicing in fact this is
the first step and you know which is the
most important step in there in ghana
yoga the path of knowledge it is this
listening not the meditation afterwards
they say Shravan arte of organum bye-bye
what you here alone knowledge comes
reasoning and meditation are to remove
obstructions in knowledge there are lot
of explanations to be done there I will
not go into it
so method listening I've been studying
reasoning and meditation one after
another in sequence so now you have the
first row of the matrix problem
ignorance of the Atman solution
knowledge of the Atman how do I get that
knowledge listen reason meditate shaman
a man and he did the asana now we again
back to scratching our heads yeah well
I've been coming to class for something
you have come for two years now I've
been coming to class for twenty years
and I don't see enlightenment coming out
anywhere close to it what is the problem
now the problem now the second tier the
second rope the problem now is what in
sanskrit is called wick shape the mind
is scattered the mind is restless
the mind is unable to absorb this
teaching clarity does not down focus
does not come we hear it even when we
apply ourselves to it the result is we
say I get some kind of intellectual
knowledge that is the sign that clarity
has not yet come so
Wyck shape a scattered mind you see
what's the problem I have gone through
your recommendation I have done hearing
and reasoning and meditation to some
extent at least for a long time it has
not worked now the problem is why has it
not worked or why is it not working many
people keep coming to class for years
and years and they have so many
notebooks and nowadays you know hard
disks full of talks and things like that
so what is happening restless mind
restless mind problem solution
concentration focus solution it's a huge
problem these days lack of attention
restlessness hyper restlessness
especially among kids Daniel Goldman who
became very famous writing EQ about the
book on emotional intelligence not one
book one after another the latest book
is written is called focus it's it's
about concentration so anyways the same
problem exactly the same problem
inability to hold on and focus on n not
just in in Vedanta in any sphere of life
in any sphere of life to do anything
great to make any kind of breakthrough
you need focus you need to hold on more
than Talent this bearing down upon it to
hold on to it something something and
seriously plug away at it for months and
years and years together that is more
important than being talented or being
very brilliant like this American saying
this a big shot a big shot is a little
shot who keeps shooting
focus the ability to hold on I have a
friend who is a mathematician tremendous
focus now he was saying that this is
what is important for to be a good
mathematician it's not really important
to be very particularly brilliant you
need talent so I said then why don't
they do it I mean it could have more
people just you need to keep doing it
he said they won't that's it they don't
they get distracted by mobile phones and
movies and socializing and so and so
forth they would I remember going to in
India this IITs are very well known
engineering colleges I went to another
engineering college to give a talk to
the students there and I was talking to
the students it's not of the rank of the
IITs a little a couple of steps down in
the ranking and I remember what I told
the students based on my observation I
said look whenever I go to a college or
university I visit the library I love
libraries I do that here also whenever I
go to a college or university and you
have fantastic libraries here when I
said here is the difference between you
guys and that elite engineering college
here I find we have extraordinary
excellent you know compute a shiny
computer departments and labs and a
beautiful library and that's what they
have in the IIT is - but here is the
difference it's not a difference in
their in your facilities it's not so
much of a difference in your faculty the
difference is this when I went to the
library just before the talk I'd gone to
visit the library so very nice where are
the kids
oh they were all gone home the computer
department rows and rows of shiny new
computers empty nobody's there
- boys and girls are sitting where are
they they have gone out in all the
socializing gone back home or something
like that
so when I went to the class which I was
supposed to address I said when I went
to that College which you guys look up
to I went and sat in the library to read
with the with the students there and
they have a group of students reading
then I went to my room to do some work
and you know took a bath and had lunch
and I came back and there was amazed to
see that eight hours later the same
students group of students was sitting
around me evidently at it exactly the
same way which they have been eight
hours earlier and I told the students
there in that College though that elite1
oh I'm so impressed how these kids in
this day and age they've got so much
focus and they said Swami you are
visiting in in the lean hours that means
if you come during exam time you will
find the kids they get get into the
library to study the moment you know
early in the morning it's open
throughout the day and they are in the
library throughout the day throughout
the evening throughout that night next
morning they go to the washroom in the
library wash their faces and go straight
to the examination house 24 hours
without a break
no coffee break no lunch no lunch no
dinner nothing sometimes they do that so
I said to those kids this is the
difference so as the professor so if
it's that why don't they do it they
won't they won't unfortunately it's not
possible everybody doesn't have that
Kepler that that kind of capacity to
hold on now focus is important focus if
if distraction is the problem Vic shaper
then the solution is a car greater
concentration and the method is
meditation
ooop asana meditation who pass on as
meditation worship meditation then
people will say back to scratching your
head again I you know I took initiation
and I have been practicing meditation
for 20 years and
Asians not particularly good I still am
so distracted and what is the problem
now
third tier the last and promises the
last year of problems we are going to
complete the matrix now the last year of
problems impurity of mind I should the
jitter in Sanskrit Cheeta mala mala
means dirt chitta mala impurity of mind
what is the solution purity of mind
jitter should dress a no-brainer purity
of mind how is that accomplished what is
the method karma yoga this is what is
coming in you karma yoga doing what
needs to be done with a spiritual
attitude spiritualizing your day-to-day
activity now you have the matrix let me
draw it again for error in your mind's
eye just draw it again first column
problem so in the first row you have got
ignorant solution knowledge method
hearing reasoning meditating gana yoga
second row problem problem is distracted
mind Sanskrit big shaper solution
focused mind Sanskrit a car Greta method
who pass on our worship meditation third
row why even meditation is not
successful third rope impure mind system
Allah impurities in the mind solution
pure mind
chitta shoddy method powerful method one
powerful method karma yoga so now you
have the matrix with a purified mind
when you sit down to meditate meditation
is immediate powerful and effective with
a concentrated and purified mind when
you approach the teaching of the Atman
there is a breakthrough you intuitively
grasp oh it is so I am the unaffected
witness consciousness tadhana andrew
baja shivoham I am pure awareness pure
bliss it is I don't have to become that
it becomes very clear and that is
realization enlightenment both he
whatever you call it drama
that happens so this is the whole
spiritual journey but again this is one
framework remember this is the framework
according to Advaita Vedanta Shankara if
you ask a teacher of bhakti they'll say
oh no no no no not like this something
else yes yes pure mind is no negative
thoughts no no no it's not that it is a
preponderance of pure thoughts you know
what will happen is spiritual life
becomes desirable and nice and not so
much of a struggle you like meditating
you like service you like reading about
you know you like reading the Gita or
the Bible or whatever it is spiritual
life becomes desirable nice interesting
and you're able to you're able to do it
that is the sign of purity of not that
once in a while and disturbance greed
reactions will not come of course they
will come how do you deal with it when
they come some people get swept away
some people get caught up in it all
right I'll give you the sign of Chitra
should be what will happen is this over
time over time what will happen is the
frequency of yes the frequency of these
upsets irritation outburst depression
inability to control myself the
frequency will go down and the second
thing which will happen will be the
intensity of these negativities will get
reduced with go down so earlier I used
to fly into a rage now I'm mildly
irritated earlier I used to be angry
almost every other day now every other
week and the recovery time will go down
earlier if I am angry in the morning
it'll take me 3 D 3 days to cool down
now if I am angry now next
moment I'm alright they were saying
shadow Raja laid down the anger of a
monk should be like a line drawn in
flowing water as soon as you draw it it
goes away it's not that anger will not
be this when we wake under said a fool
cannot get angry
the wise one does not get angry so yes
this is a monk in Chennai he told me
this this is a good way to measure your
progress in spiritual life it happens
over time it is gently even even without
any kind of specific spiritual practice
maturity is what we could call this is
what is called maturity emotional
maturity is this thing the frequency of
problems the intensity of problems and
the recovery time from the problems they
all go down or what years you will
notice it is happening yes yes and now
does do you lose the ability to focus
yes and no if you if you do not keep in
training you will lose these abilities
so I have seen students who became
academicians researchers they retain the
ability to focus because they are
focusing a student who goes into
managing a multinational corporation
with a hundred and everything all are a
busy mom so very difficult to focus on
one thing because half a dozen things
are calling for your attention I saw a
cartoon it was a philosophy journal the
issue the time the theme was time so the
cartoon was
on one side is the old man with a side
standing it's written father time you
know he's looking brooding father time
old man and the next picture is of this
lady she's got a handbag and two kids
hanging onto a hand and a bun the kid on
the prime and racing along she looks
harried it says mother not enough time
father time and mothered not enough time
so sometimes you are put in a situation
where it's difficult to focus but even
they had notice the person who can focus
we get much more done much better than
the person who cannot focus yeah and
these practices help you to maintain and
develop your power of focus meditation
it does it does help the ability to sit
still and hold on to one thought for a
while that is the very essence of
concentration a focus now is there's so
much emphasis on mindfulness it's it's a
huge thing in USA now children are being
taught mindfulness not just for focus
for calming down for distressing but for
focus also for awareness yes oh you
noticed god somebody's noticing yes
there's a difference there's a big
difference the meditation which is done
in the first one that is called needd
asana vedantic meditation the meditation
which is done in earlier in the second
row that is the yogic meditation that is
dianna or rope asana now there is a
difference I will not go into that but
if you want I will refer you to a
parochial booty I have a series of
lectures towards the end of those
lectures in a production of booty from
verses 101 onwards Shankar Acharya talks
about vedantic meditation that is the
ro1 kind of meditation but he also
contrasts it with the yogic meditation
the purpose of a the Vedantic meditation
is to realize that I am Brahman the
purpose of yogic meditation is to
develop the power of focus I'll leave it
at that but there are there is a
difference in principle there and in
practice also alright and this is as
much as I wanted to say this is the
framework and we will use this
throughout our study of Gita but
remember this is just a framework you if
you did come to some other spiritual
tradition they may have a different
framework the bhakti traditions for
example they will never say karma yoga
then OPA sauna and then Jana Yoga no no
work the alone beginning middle and end
bhakti devotion you want purity of mind
but the devotion will give it to you you
want focus
love what gives you more focus than love
and you want knowledge and love of God
will give you knowledge ultimately God
will give you knowledge so all will come
from love are they wrong no not wrong
that's another another way of looking at
it but Advait Vedanta the approach is
like this all right having said this let
us go on I am NOT going too much into
this karma Bandhan prahasta see by
following karma yoga you will overcome
the bondage of karma what does that mean
Krishna himself explains 40
my hobby Cremona Asti main hobby Cremona
Asti Pratibha unibit dirty practive
alone a bit dirty so album a pleasure
Monsieur
so album pure Monsieur trotty Mahato by
art therapy mahoto by art in this
practice karmayoga in contrast to
worldly karma action in the world
worldly action family job whatever it is
in contrast to that worldly karma this
karma yoga when you're doing the same
action but when you change your attitude
and make it to Karma Yoga what will
happen there is no wastage you begin
something do not complete it is it you
have to write it off total loss no
whatever you do it goes towards your
spiritual progress if that's what you're
interested in spiritual progress then
pretty of Ayane with deity there is no
opposite effect or no bad effect no side
effects to this medicine then
so welcome appreciated Monsieur try at a
Mahato Fiat whatever little you practice
gives result
it protects uses from great fear the
fear of birth then death the fear of
samsara even a little bit of practice
not that you have to become a
Vivekananda and Buddha and then only you
get the result oh no then very very few
people would practice it but to the
extent that we are spiritual to the
extent that you pray to the extent that
you meditate to the extent that you
study and think about it so that extent
you will get peace of mind you will get
joy you will get strength I have seen
many times people who say that oh I've
been doing with meditation or violent or
something Buddhism for a long time not I
haven't really gone gotten much out of
it I mean I have not really advanced and
so many problems still remain and when I
say all right stop it then give it up oh
no no no I can't do that in many of
these cases they will say in most cases
they will say that is the most precious
thing in my life now ah
then how
can you say that you have not got
anything I remember when I became a monk
as a novice three days afterwards I told
another monk not a very senior monk were
too scared to approach the very senior
ones a fairly middling level monk I said
oh nothing is happening I mean I'm not
progressing three days into the monastic
life and he shot back with something
I'll never forget he said okay go back
home I said no I can't do that I can't
admit it really could not imagine going
back home then he said look that place
you call home for 23 years has within
three days become unthinkable for you is
that not progress
it's incredible progress not that it's
become very bad it's exactly what it was
earlier but now you have got a taste of
something which there's no comparison
you would rather keep on doing this I
remember some of those things with the
early lessons we learned really
worthwhile I'll share a couple the first
day it was a monastery at at the school
attached to it it's in ramakrishna
mission with their pd ochre
so third or fourth day when i was there
one of the monks took me to the school
to teach the kids and he introduced me
to the teachers the teachers there
they're some of the monks teach and
there are other teachers who are paid
teachers you know like it teaches in any
school any high school but the monks and
the teachers work together so when I was
introduced here is this young boy who
has come to be a monk and he's going to
work in the school for the time being
and the Swami was introducing me said he
has got these qualifications these
degrees and things like that and once
senior teacher an old gentleman he said
ah we are lucky to have him then God's a
qualified by we're lucky to have him and
immediately the Swami said correcting
him no he is lucky to be here
look that correction do you see what I
mean
that consider it the greatest blessing
of your life that you are accepted into
this holy order we are not lucky to have
you
you are lucky to be here and I said it's
just a great lesson to learn for the
rest of my life
that was one one day I think I was
sweeping the road beneath building or
something like that and one senior not a
senior monk a monk was just senior to me
just a few years more than me he was
going from there to the main monastery
was leaving and I was going to take his
place and by leaving he left me with a
little bit of advice he said look the
sweeping you're doing suppose they tell
you all the rest of your life in your
monastic life the only thing that you'll
ever be good for is just sweeping this
road and I don't have the emotional I
guess why I said it's perfectly all
right with me I'm ready to keep sweeping
this room for the road for the rest of
my life just if you let me stay here
then he was so happy he was not a young
man
little a few years older than me he said
that's the attitude if you have that
attitude you'll be a good monk now so
these are this is the spirit of karma
yoga yeah and we saw so much of this all
right
Neha Vikram on our show Asti
worldly action if you begin it you must
complete it you can't sow the seeds to
have a farmer can't do that and and then
you have to you have to you know prepare
the field and sow the seeds and then
water rate irrigate it and then put
fertilizers and stuff and supplements
and so on and then harvest the crops but
suppose somebody says um I'll do
maybe I'll sew the seeds rest I will not
do so won't I get 1/4 of the crops no
you
won't it'll be a total loss you start
producing a new gadget you invented it
good and then you start producing it but
if you don't produce it and take it all
the way to the consumer to the consumer
you won't get a penny back until you
complete a world reaction no results are
there now that applies for religious
actions also which are done for worldly
purposes so the puja which is done for a
particular it's called Sakura Appa sana
Sakuma karma karma done with desire I
want money so many things the the first
part of the Vedas are full of what are
called against sacrifices fire
sacrifices basically you're bribing God
to help you hurt
I mean I'm putting it in a very general
sense you I offered this and I want this
in life what do you want something in
this life
let the rains be good to us let disease
not touch our community you know what
what persons would have hoped for 2000
3000 years ago
protect us from our enemies and so on so
forth now all of those rituals this is a
saying that you must perform them
properly they must be performed just
like any work you do in the world they
must be done perfectly then only the
result is expected do it half may
half-assedly no we don't get anything
but in contrast to that he says Karma
Yoga for liberation for enlightenment
for love of God whatever you do it is
not ruined even if you don't bring it to
a completion you chant the name of God a
thousand times good you chant it ten
times still good chanted chant it once
still good not that you will do it
half-assedly the puja but if it's an
offering of love they say why go near
the small defects in the puja God does
not look at those because it's an
offering of love you don't want anything
in return
you just offering it out of love you
want you said no I want purification of
mine didn't you just say result is
purification that's all right
the desire for God is not
we counted among desires so Ramakrishna
put it this way and somebody asked Swami
you say you're giving up desires to
become a monkey bus give up designs but
do you want God or not yes then you have
a desire shri ramakrishna has answered
to that the desire for God is not to be
counted among results he says the sugar
candy is not to be counted among other
candy because candy says causes acidity
and is it acid reflux and sugar candy is
something that destroys acidity you have
to be a Bengali to understand that I
think so mystery yes so that is not to
be counted rock candy rock candy that is
not to be counted among sweets though it
tastes sweet so this desire for God
wipes out all worldly desire and takes
you beyond worldliness so that is not to
be counted as a worldly desire so there
is no loss on this path that's the point
number one number one was it takes you
beyond the bondage of karma that was in
39th verse and these three there is no
loss there is no negative effect and
also a little bit of practice saves you
from great fear these are the
explanations of that one the first one
there is no negative effect side effect
it's a but the avaya is an adverse
effect an unintended consequence these
there are there are actually forces you
can call them psychic forces beyond our
ordinary knowledge and these whether the
Vedic fire sacrifices or the tantric
practices they play with these forces in
order to get certain certain results in
our worldly life now if you do not if
you're not careful it can be damaging
like a powerful medicine if you don't
take it in proper dosage if you don't
take it with proper diet it can have
unintended side effects sometimes the
side effects are much worse and much are
very dangerous can land you up in
hospital the same way many religious
acts are there which are prescribed in
the Vedas for worldly benefits
and if you don't do it properly it can
lead to harm so immediately in the mind
of the Vedic practitioners the question
was this thing you're going to teach
karma yoga this Gita gana our meditation
Karma all this you're teaching do they
have any side effects negative effects
adverse if I don't do it well no they
don't
there's no cite that no harmful
consequence to it whatsoever
anything that you do for spirituality
for the love of God for God realization
put it which see I'm using two kinds of
words self realization or spirituality
or the way I say or God realization
means the same thing in advaitha vedanta
you can say both ways
they have knows no negative consequences
no negative consequences there is a
story I it is traditionally told so
there's I'll tell that story and end
here the story of Britt restaura when
you're talking about negative
consequences it's as an illustration
always that the traditional teacher will
tell the story but we have had many
Indian children didn't know the story I
knew it from those emerge it tregurtha
comics the story goes like this
in the ancient days of the wars between
the demons and the gods the sage washed
out his son whose name was surprised
surprised vishwaroopa who was also a
sage he was killed by mistake by Indra
the king of the gods and Twista was
furious
with the king of the gods Indra and so
he wanted to destroy Indra the king of
the gods so he performed this elaborate
Vedic sacrifice this kind of work with a
specific worldly desire or otherworldly
desire the desire was the demon who will
be born of this sacrifice will be
manifested by this a supernatural force
a demon terrifying demon that demon will
be powerful enough to kill the king of
the gods so there's an elaborate
procedure to generate this force the
demon now the story goes the mantra
which is to be chanted while the fire
sacrifice is going on in Russia
Thrun what does one in the English
octoroon what does well it really means
let the enemy of Indra develop or grow
or manifest now there is a specific way
of chanting vedic mantras where you have
to put stress on the intonation it is
connected to the way of chanting and
grammar in a very intricate way we will
not go into the details but suffice it
for this much if you say in Russia true
but what does wha
it means let the one who will destroy
the enemy of Indra who will destroy
Indra let let that one come out this is
what the the sage wanted but now the
gods knew that our King is in danger so
they conspired and the goddess of
learning Saraswathi she manifested on
the tongue of the the rishi the moment
he was about to chant at that time a
tongue twisted so she made it so that
the rashid chanted it wrongly instead of
putting the emphasis on the last
syllable in russia through he said in
russia through what thus were let he who
will be destroyed by indra let him be
manifested the meaning changes
immediately depending on where you put
the stress because why again there is oh
there is two types of Sanskrit okay I
will not go into details grammatical
conjunctions samatha with that such
teeth are purified Purusha and baristas
so if you on depending on pronunciation
the the grammatical conjunction changes
and so the meaning changes and so he
made a mistake and what he wanted
happened a terrible demon came up and
went out and fought against the gods and
defeated the gods and defeated indra i
think he swallowed in drawer something
like that or things like that
now what happened was Indra had gone to
the great sage Dadhichi so story within
story and they said that only a weapon
the Thunderbolt
in fact Indra is called the wielder of
the Thunderbolt Raja the Thunderbolt can
destroy this demon nothing else can
destroy this demon so what is the
Thunderbolt means so you can see Indra
is also the god of rain and thunder so
what what he uses when there's a
thunderstorm that is interest in the
Thunderbolt so where will this
Thunderbolt be produced will boy make it
or not drop or Lockheed laughs so it is
the sage Dadhichi the most righteous
among sages his bones will are enough
above are required to make this
Thunderbolt so it is a person who has
led a life of perfect a perfectly
ethical and moral life so they go how
can you ask this we want your bones and
the sage she was so unattached to his
worldly existence he said all right I
shall go I'm going to give up my body
India yogic meditation it sat in
meditation and left the body you can use
the bones and so they manufactured the
Thunderbolt out of the bones and Indra
using the Thunderbolt finally killed the
demon Vitra so from then on Indra that
king of the Gods is known as the wielder
of the budget of a leader of the
Thunderbolt and so on so the story this
is like that but the point here is that
the wrong pronunciation led to a wrong -
absolutely opposite effect so for all
worldly kinds even though our religious
ritual but if your desires are worldly
then you have to be very careful of how
you perform the ritual but for karma
yoga bhakti yoga gana yoga whatever you
do for the love of God all right
this the specifics don't count so much
in which it is a nice fable practically
practically big thing I remember our the
head of our monastery the one we were
trained under he taught us these
beautiful lessons he said it's not the
work that you
that matters it's what the work does to
you that matters what did you get out of
it not what did you do in the world
outside so sometimes we've as in the
enthusiastic newcomers we made mistakes
he was not worried about that he would
see that did we try did we do it with
the proper attitude and did we learned
from it that's all
sometimes mushroom which didn't have
much money it suffered there was
somebody who you know a biogas plant and
some things so one of the Bromwich eyes
was in charge of that he messed up and
the thing failed and the ashram lost
20,000 rupees and we thought he is going
to be in serious trouble now and the
Swami was not at all concerned he said
I'll raise the money somehow but the
thing is what lesson do you take out of
it what lesson do you take out of it how
do you grow spiritually that's what's
important in work not the worldly result
that's the difference between worldly
work and karma yoga but don't try it
with your boss I have grown spiritually
boss but about the bottom line the
bottom line is dropped out then you are
in trouble all right we will go on with
this next time Oh
chanty shanti shanti hurry he owned that
such sri ramakrishna Aparna must this
subject will go on from that this 39th
verse up to 53rd verse the subject of
karma yoga then there'll be a change in
subject again when Arjuna will ask the
question how do we know a person has
become enlightened so by what signs that
will be the last topic of this chapter